Finding Aid for Department of History (University of Michigan) Senior Honors Theses
Bentley Historical Library
Department of History (University of Michigan) senior honors theses
1969-2011
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Dept. of History.
921114 Bimu C27 2
5.25 linear feet
Research papers on topics relating to Michigan history and the history of the University of Michigan written by students in the History Department Undergraduate Honors Program.
This collection was transferred from the History Department (donor no. 1442 ) in 1990.
The collection is open for research with the exception of several theses for which student release forms are not on file. In compliance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act, theses without release forms are closed for 75 years.
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Student educational records: FERPA's protection of personally identifiable information in a student's education records ends at the time of a student's death and therefore is a matter of institutional policy. As a courtesy to the families of recently deceased students who were enrolled at the time of death, the University generally will not release information from their education records for five years without the consent of the deceased student's next of kin. Eighty-five (85) years after the date the records were first created, the University will presume that the student is deceased. Thereafter the student's education records will be open. Student records at the Bentley Historical Library are restricted for eighty-five (85) years, but may also be made available upon proof of the death of the student.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
The Department of History deposits more recent Senior Honors Theses in the University of Michigan's Deep Blue digital repository.
This is a collection of senior honors theses written by University of Michigan students in the department of history. Only topics relating to the history of Michigan or the history of the University of Michigan have been retained in this collection.
The papers are organized by year of completion and thereunder alphabetically by author.
Academic freedom.; Afro-Americans -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Afro-Americans -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Agriculture -- Michigan.; Air -- Pollution -- Law and legislation -- United States.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.) -- Schools.; Automobile industry and trade -- United States.; Child abuse.; Child development.; Crematoriums.; Death.; Demography.; Detroit (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.) -- Politics and government.; Elections -- United States -- 1968.; Fertility, Human.; Housing -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Indians of North America -- Michigan -- Claims.; Jews -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Labor -- Michigan.; Ludington (Mich.); Mason County (Mich.); Michigan -- History.; New Deal, 1933-1939 -- Michigan.; American newspapers -- Michigan.; Northwest, Old.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1840.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1968.; Strikes and lockouts -- Michigan.; Trade-unions -- Michigan.; Undertakers and undertaking -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Washtenaw County (Mich.); Washtenaw County (Mich.) -- Politics and government.; Minority college students -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Education and the war.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Women in the labor movement -- Michigan -- Flint.; Women -- Michigan -- Washtenaw County.; Teachers -- Michigan.; Women teachers -- Michigan.; Children -- Death -- Psychological aspects.; Women -- Michigan -- Attitudes.; Women -- Massachusetts -- Attitudes.; Women -- Education -- Michigan.; Marriage -- Michigan.; Saline Valley Farms (Saline, Mich.); Cooperative societies -- Michigan.; Immigrants -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Irish Americans -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Polar Bear Expedition.; Soviet Union -- History -- Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; Recombinant DNA -- Research.; Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; Coughlin, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1891-1979.; Detroit Urban League.; Dieterle, Enoch, 1865-; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; General Motors Corporation.; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft and Agricultural Implement Workers of America.; Industrial Workers of the World.; Lakewood Crematory.; Merrill-Palmer Institute.; Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Sligh, Charles R., Jr. (Charles Robert), 1906-1997.; Stone, Ralph, 1868-1956.; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); University of Michigan -- Sports.; University of Michigan. Band.; University of Michigan -- History.; University of Michigan -- Students.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Sunrise Cooperative Farm Community.; Planned Parenthood League, Inc (Detroit, Mich.); University of Michigan -- Admission.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Political activity.; Word of God (Religious community); Michigan Central Railroad Depot (Detroit, Mich.)
- Senior Honors Theses
  - Undated
    - Schettenhelm, Karl W., Prelude to power politics: The isolationism of Senator Arthur H. Vandenberg, [1] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick, 1884-1951)
  - 1969
    - Koenig, Martha Jean., Flames of Hysteria: The "Red" scare in Detroit, 1919-1920, [2] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Detroit (Mich.))
  - 1973
    - Kubick, Theodore R., Study and analysis of two moderately planned controlled income townhouse developments, [3] (Box 1)
      (concerns developments near Ann Arbor, Michigan)
      (Subject Terms: Ann Arbor (Mich.), Housing--Michigan--Ann Arbor)
  - 1974
    - Greenberg, Susan B. and Jeffrey S. Englander., Child abuse: Dealing with the problem in Washtenaw County, [4] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Child abuse, Washtenaw County (Mich.))
    - Rothschild, Steven B., A general history of the Detroit Jewish community: 1933-1949, [5] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Detroit (Mich.), Jews, American--Michigan--Detroit.)
    - Spaulding, Paul P., III., The extinquishment of the Indian land claim in the Old Northwest, 1780-1795, [6] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Indians of North America--Michigan--Claims, Northwest, Old)
    - Yeghissian, Patricia., Emergence of the Red Tams: Women's Emergency Brigade, Flint Sit-down Strike of 1936-1937, [7] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Strikes and lockouts, Women--History)
  - 1976
    - Good, Deborah., The Lakewood Crematory controversy, [8] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Ann Arbor (Mich.), Crematoriums, Death, Lakewood Crematory)
    - Kanengiser, Amy., The development of a radical ideology in SDS, [9] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.))
    - Leech, Frederick C., Vertical integration and market power: A case study of General Motors, [10] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Automobile industry and trade, General Motors Corporation)
    - Nason, Andrew S., A case study of industrial union #440 of the IWW during the depression 1929-1938, [11] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: International Workers of the World, Labor and labor classes, Trade-unions)
    - O'Keefe, Kurt A., Hazen S. Pingree: An analysis of his vote for mayor and its effect on the municipal elections 1887 to 1897, [12] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Detroit (Mich.), Detroit (Mich.)--Politics and government, Pingree, Hazen Smith, 1840-1901.)
    - Swartzentruber, Anne., The undertaking practice of Enoch Dieterle in Ann Arbor, Michigan 1897-1918, [13] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Dieterle, Enoch, 1895-, Ann Arbor (Mich.), Undertakers and undertaking)
    - Trierweiler, William C., The differential child-woman ratios in Washtenaw County, Michigan, 1850 An investigation into the patterns of fertility decline in ante-bellum America, [14] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Demography, Fertility, Human, Washtenaw County (Mich.) Women--History)
    - Weingarten, Ann., Women common school teachers in Michigan, 1836-1860 A study of their economic, social, and occupational characteristics, [15] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Teachers, Women--History)
  - 1977
    - De Bofsky, Mark D., Mirror of the depression--Father Charles E. Coughlin and his social movement, [16] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Coughlin, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1891-1979)
    - Ellis, Barbara June., Fertility on the northern lumbering frontier: Ludington and four townships, Mason County, Michigan, 1880, [17] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Fertility, Human, Ludington (Mich.), Mason County (Mich.))
    - Kane, Regina Naomi., The history of the University of Michigan Marching Band, [18] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: University of Michigan. Band, University of Michigan--History)
    - Runyan, Betsy., Academic freedom at the University of Michigan, 1954, [19] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Academic freedom, University of Michigan--History)
    - Vener, Erica R., The failure of George Romney's 1968 presidential campaign, [20] (Box 1)
      (Subject Terms: Elections--United States--1968 Presidents--United States--Elections--1968 Romney, George W., 1907-)
  - 1978
    - McConnell, Stuart C., The peculiar interest of the country: Newspapering on the Marquette iron range of Michigan's Upper Peninsula, 1857-1884, [21] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Newspapers, Upper Peninsula (Mich.))
  - 1979
    - Downs, Peter., A history of agriculture in Michigan since World War Two, [22] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Agriculture)
    - Gorosh, Steven J., Reformers, radicals & revolutionaries: Students for a Democratic Society in Ann Arbor, 1960-1970, [23] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Ann Arbor (Mich.), Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.))
    - Spivak, Frank J., Toward a corporate debut; The emergence of public relations at General Motors from 1933 to 1945, [24] (Box 2)
  - 1980
    - Benjamin, Sally D., The Merrill-Palmer Institute: Its formative role in the beginnings of the scientific study of child development, [25] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Child development, Merrill-Palmer Institute)
    - Silver, Kenneth F., The Dead End Kids: A history of Local 212 UAW-CIO, [26] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America., Labor and labor classes, Trade-unions)
  - 1982
    - Amith, Adina N., Building a well being society of well being individuals: The activities and attitudes of the Detroit Urban League during the Great Migration, 1916-1921, [27] (Box 2)
      [Subject Terms: Detroit (Mich.), Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit
    - Wolper, Gregg., The New Deal in Ann Arbor, [28] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: New Deal, 1933-1939)
  - 1984
    - DiPrinzio, Raymond Anthony., Henry Carter Adams: A progressive speaks for himself, 1887-1907, [29] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.)
    - Kemp, John W., Riding out the storm: The University of Michigan during World War II, [30] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: University of Michigan--History, University of Michigan--Wars, emergencies, etc. (World War, 1939-1945))
    - Shufro, Nicholas A., The Great Depression's effect on enrollment patterns at the University of Michigan from 1929 to 1939, [31] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: University of Michigan--History)
  - 1985
    - London, Jacob., Walter Reuther's moment: One man's struggle to increase labor's role in political and economic decision-making 1940-1946, [32] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America., Labor and labor classes, Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970)
    - Sudarkasa, Michael Eric., Black varsity lettermen: 1882-1979 Offering a window onto the historical experience of Black students at the University of Michigan, [33] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Afro-Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor, University of Michigan--History, University of Michigan--Minority students)
    - Thompson, Heather Ann., Detroit: Wildcat 1973, [34] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Detroit (Mich.), International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America., Strikes and lockouts)
  - 1986
    - Bacon, John U., The process and results of Ann Arbor secondary school curriculum reform, [34-a] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Ann Arbor (Mich.), Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Schools)
    - Barnes, Katrina A., Truman, Vandenberg, and the Cold War: Anti-Communism and bipartisanship as political necessities, [34-b] (Box 2)
    - Rapaport, John., George Romney and the 1969-1973 FHA housing crisis, [34-c] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Romney, George, 1907-1995)
    - Sullivan, Bradley J., The role of businessmen in progressive politics: The case study of Charles Sligh, [34-d] (Box 2)
      (Subject Terms: Sligh, Charles Robert, 1906-)
  - 1987
    - Kannensohn, Kim., The struggle for acceptance: The response of the American Jewish community to Henry Ford's antisemitic campaign, 1920-1927, [35] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Jews, American--Michigan--Detroit.)
    - Paetkau, Tyler., Cooperation in a crisis: student, faculty, and administration interaction at the University of Michigan, 1965-1970, [36] (Box 3)
    - Simon, Amy R., Attitudes of women toward the death of their children in Michigan and Massachusetts from 1830-1890, [37] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Death Women--History)
  - 1990
    - Abramson, Jerome., Clean Air Act automobile regulations and the Ford administration, [38] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Air - Pollution - Law and legislation - United States Ford, Gerald R., 1910-)
    - Jampel, Emily S., Secondary education in nineteenth century Michigan: Community-wide attitudes and the development of high school education for women, [39] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Education Women--History)
    - Topetzes, James Gregory., Foundations of partisanship in the presidential election of 1840 Washtenaw County, Michigan, [40] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Presidents--United States--Elections--1840, Washtenaw County (Mich.) - Politics and government, 1840)
  - 1991
    - Allen, James P., The tragic reformer: Ralph Stone, Progressive in the New Deal, [41] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Stone, Ralph, 1868-1956.)
    - Hunter, Daniel Francis, The Irish in a Town and Village Environment: A Probe of the 1860 Census in Ann Arbor and Vicinity, [42] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Ann Arbor (Mich.), Irish, American--Michigan--Ann Arbor)
    - LaLonde, Kristine, Student Activism in the Student Newspaper: The University of Michigan in the 1930s, [43] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Newspapers, University of Michigan--History, University of Michigan--Students--Political activity.)
    - Ray, Anne, "Yours with a heap of love": Marriage, gender, and Civil War correspondence, [44] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: United States - History - Civil War, 1861-1865, Women--History)
  - 1992
    - Buskirk, Amy L., American Visions: The Goals and Realities of Saline Valley Farms and Sunrise Cooperative Farm Community, [45] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Cooperative societies--Michigan, Saline Valley Farms (Saline, Mich.), Sunrise Cooperative Farm Community.)
    - Martin, Elizabeth, Detroit and the Great Migration, 1916-1929, [46] (Box 3)
    - Miller, Karen R, "Hate" Strikes in Detroit During World War II, [47] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Automobile industry and trade, Detroit (Mich.), Strikes and lockouts)
    - Mutchnick, Ian, Regulating Recombinant DNA at the University of Michigan: "An Act of Faith", [48] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Recombinant DNA--Research., University of Michigan--History, University of Michigan--Research)
  - 1993
    - Bell, Denise C, Weathering the Storm: Women's Athletics at the University of Michigan, 1973-1981, [49] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: University of Michigan--Athletics, University of Michigan--History, Women--History)
    - Gendleman, Amy Beth, The History of Planned Parenthood in Southeastern Michigan, 1927-1974, [50] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Planned Parenthood--Michigan)
  - 1995
    - Dombkowski, Kristen "To Raise the Average": The Introduction and Development of Kindergartens in Michigan to 1910, [54] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Kindergarten--Michigan, Teachers)
    - Kent, Joshua D. Safe but not secure: Jewish American Responses to Organized Antisemitism in Detroit During the Crisis Years, 1937-1946, [55] (Box 3)
      [Student records restricted, no signed release form]
      (Subject Terms: Antisemitism, Jews, American--Michigan-Detroit, Detroit (Mich.))
    - Mejer, Adrienne "Sisters-in-Law": Pioneer Women Law Graduates from the University of Michigan Law School, 1870-1920, [56] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: University of Michigan--History, University of Michigan--Law School, Women--History)
  - 1996
    - Baum, Mark The Fight to End In Loco Parentis: A Study of the University of Michigan's Paternal Housing and Educational Policies and the Students' Response, 1955-1975, [57] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Student-administrator relationships, University of Michigan--History)
    - Becker, Julie "On Common Ground:" Detroit's Intercultural Education Movement, 1943-1952, [58] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Multi-cultural education, University of Michigan--Admissions)
    - Bellows, Benjamin W. Politics and Michigan Fiscal Policy, 1837-1865, [59] (Box 3)
      (Subject Terms: Fiscal policy)
    - Galed, Tamar Hill Auditorium: A Symbol of Higher Education's Promises, [60] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: University of Michigan--History, Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan))
    - Perez, Devon Anne The Dodge Revolutionary Union Movement: Rhetoric Defined, Actions Solidified, Opposition Destroyed, [61] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Dodge Revolutionary Union Movement, Labor and labor classes)
  - 1997
    - Etcubañez, Marita C. The Filipino American Community in Detroit: Expressions of Identity, [66] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Detroit (Mich.), Filipino Americans)
    - Lopez, Sean Christopher Realizations of Broadacre City: Frank Lloyd Wright's Postwar Planned Communities, [67] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: City Planning - Michigan)
    - Naftulin, Danielle Eve The Advent of the Juvenile Court and Robison v. Wayne Circuit Judges: Progressivism and the Michigan Supreme Court, [68] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Michigan. Supreme Court)
    - Quinn, Andrew Sekou The Detroit Riot of 1863: Racial Violence and Internal Division in Northern Society During the Civil War, [69] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit, Michigan--History--Civil War, 1861-1865, Race relations 1860-1870.)
    - Santana, Kennet D. Genesis of a Ghetto: Urban Renewal and Dislocation in Battle Creek, Michigan, 1947-1961, [70] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Afro-Americans--Michigan--Battle Creek, City Planning - Michigan)
  - 1998
    - Bauman, John E. Superfly Suits and Blue Suits with Silver Badges: STRESS, the Election of Coleman Young, and the Reform of the Detroit Police Department, [71] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit, Detroit (Mich.), Detroit (Mich.)--Politics and government)
    - Sirna, David A. Prosperity and Poverty, Black Flint, 1900-1990 A Study in Paradox, [72] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Afro-Americans--Michigan--Flint, General Motors Corporation, Labor and labor classes)
  - 1999
    - Bernstein, Scott Howard. The American North Russian Expeditionary Force, 1918-1919, [51] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Polar Bear Expedition, 1918-1919, Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920)
    - Gongora, Alan. The Changing Function of Public Education: Selective Admissions at the University of Michigan, 1920-1940, [52] (Box 4)
    - Wu, Gregory K. Subversion of Immigrant Rights in Detroit, A Study of Cultural Struggle, 1910-1918, [53] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Detroit (Mich.), Immigrants--Michigan--Detroit)
  - 2002
    - Daniels, Benjamin The Detroit May oral Election of 1969 A Study of Race and Retrenchment, [62] (Box 4)
    - Morris, Robert Preserving the Union as it Was: The Michigan Democratic Party During the Civil War, [63] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Michigan--History--Civil War, 1861-1865)
    - Shirvell, Andrew Echoes of An Earlier Crusade: The Right to Life of Michigan's Struggle Against the National Status Quo, [64] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Michigan State Anti-slavery Society, Pro-life movement, Right to Life of Michigan)
    - Tausig, Ben Detroit Techno: Race, Agency, and Electronic Music in Post-Industrial Detroit, [65] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit, Detroit (Mich.), Techno music)
  - 2003
    - Luckhardt, Traci Towards a More Secular School: The Changing Face of Detroit Public Schools, 1890s -1920s, [73] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Detroit (Mich.), Education)
    - Miller, Sarah K. Walking a Tightrope: Race and Politics in Detroit, [74] (Box 4)
    - Robbins, Mark Walter Rationality in an Age of Ill-Reason: American Anxiety and the Reactions of Michigan Agricultural College [M.A.C.] and the University of Michigan to the First Red Scare, [75] (Box 4)
      (Subject Terms: Communism--Michigan, University of Michigan--Students--Political activity.,)
  - 2004
    - Goodspeed, Robert C. Urban Renewal in Postwar Detroit: The Gratiot Area Redevelopment, A Case Study, [76] (Box 5)
      (Subject Terms: Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit, City Planning - Michigan)
    - Hutton, Michelle Rebekah White Picket Fences and Black City Lights: Urban Transformation and Racial Turnover in Southfield, [77] (Box 5)
    - Jones, Olivia Helena Housewives for a Separate Black Economy: The Detroit Housewives League of the 1930s Great Depression Era, [78] (Box 5)
      (Subject Terms: Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit, Women--History)
    - Lambe, Kristy Getting the Ducks Out of the Bathtub: The Hygiene and Americanization Campaigns of the Ford Sociological Department, 1914-1921, [79] (Box 5)
      (Subject Terms: Automobile industry and trade, Ford Motor Company, Immigrants--Michigan--Detroit)
    - Lowthian, Robert Decline of an Urban Empire, [80] (Box 5)
      (Subject Terms: African-Americans--Michigan--Flint, General Motors Corporation)
  - 2005
    - Broad, Trevor A Forgotten Man in a Tumultuous Time: The Gilded Age as Seen by United States Supreme Court Associate Justice Henry Billings Brown, [81] (Box 5)
      (Subject Terms: Brown, Henry Billings)
    - Hiedemann, Sabrina Unique Collections, Innovative Designs, and One Interpretation: The Henry Ford Museum, 1929-1976, [82] (Box 5)
      (Subject Terms: Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village – History, Ford, Henry, Historical Museums)
    - Horowitz, Susan Peace, Protests, and Parties: The Radical Student Movement Against War and Fascism in America, 1933-1939, [83] (Box 5)
      (Subject Terms: College Students – Political Activity, Protest movements – United States)
    - Mobley, W. Patrick Disease, Rhetoric, and Action: Cholera in Detroit, 1832 and 1834, [84] (Box 5)